So today, we're going to
talk about architecture,
which, at least to me, has
always been pretty inscrutable.
And so I'm going to take the
approach of just telling you
everything.
I'm going to go through
all of the modern papers.
And we're going to just look
through what has everyone done.
And so I've titled
this everything
you didn't want to know
about architectures
and hyperparameters,
because I think we all
wished we lived in a world,
where the only things you had
to know were like VC
dimension or something, very
simple theoretical tools, but
that's not really where we are.
OK.
What we are going
to do is, we are
going to try to understand
architecture from a survey lens.
The best thing to do, better
than listening to this lecture,
even, is for you to go out,
and train your own models,
and try different architectures.
That's, by far, the
best thing to do.
That's part of the
philosophy of the course.
But we're not going to be
able to cover the whole design
space of all the different
architectures that
are out there.
That's not something that we
have the compute or the time
to do.
So my opinion is, the second
best thing that we could do
is to try to learn from
the experience of others.
What has everyone else done?
What are the choices
that they are making?
And by looking at a broader,
somewhat zoomed out picture,
maybe we can start
to understand,
oh, these are the kinds
of parameters and choices
that are fixed across all
effective architectures.
And these other ones can
be varied without impacting
how the model perform.
So I'm going to talk about,
basically, transformer variants,
like, what is the modern
transformer starting
with the Vaswani paper?
And then as we go
to more modern, more
recent architectures, what
do they have in common?
And then what are we allowed
to vary or not allowed?
But what do people vary
as they go through this.
So I think many of you have
taken an NLP course of some kind
or at least seen a transformer.
So you've probably seen the
very vanilla transformer
from Vaswani, et al.
There's some fairly standard
choices that you make.
You say, oh, transformers don't
have positional dependence,
so we're going to add
a position embedding.
And what do we do, we're going
to add some sines and cosines.
We're going to have information
processing through ReLU.
And then we're going
to have a post norm.
I'll talk about what
exactly that is later.
And when you look at
your assignment, your A1,
you're going to notice some
differences between the standard
or the vanilla
transformer and what
we've asked you to implement.
Well, we're going to ask
you to move the LayerNorm
to the front of each transformer
block or the nonresidual layers.
We're going to ask you to
implement something called RoPE.
And we're going to ask you
to implement something called
SwiGLU GeLU and not ReLU.
Why do we pick these?
One reason is, we've copied a
lot of this over from but Llama,
so did everyone else.
Really, I think, if you were to
train your own language model,
I think you'll quickly
run into this question,
oh, there's so many choices.
What do I choose for
all of these things?
And so let's now walk through
all of these different models?
The way I think
about architectures
is to look at all the different
things people have done
and say, what are the things
that people have done?
Can we pick and
choose from those?
Percy always makes fun of
me for this a little bit,
but I try to look at all
the different models that
come out each year to
try to make this lecture.
And last year, I thought, oh,
there's just a couple papers.
It's going to be fine.
And then I look
through all the things,
and there's a lot of papers.
There's Qwen2, and
Gemma 3, and InternLM2.
And then there were even more.
There's Nemotron-4 and Qwen2.
And oh, my goodness, there
were 19 new dense models.
And so last year, I had
my work cut out for me.
And this year, I thought,
well, there can't
be that many new LLM releases.
It's got to be slowing down.
People can't keep training
20 dense LLMs per year.
And that's technically right,
there aren't as many dense LLMs.
Initially, I was like,
oh, there's Qwen3.
Gemma 4 just came
out last Thursday,
so I put that in
there, and Olmo 3.
There's only a couple.
And of course, I have
to give a shout out
to Percy's own AP model
trained with Marin.
And I was like, oh, we'll just
have a few things to cover.
But it turns out, if
you start looking,
there's a lot of
different models.
And so the fact that we have
so many different models,
most of these actually are
MoEs, mixtures of experts.
And I'll be talking about that
tomorrow rather than today.
Because we have such a
big diversity of models,
we actually get a
pretty good picture
of all the different
choices that we can make.
So I made this little table.
We'll come back to this little
table at the end of the lecture.
But basically, at
this point, starting
with the original
transformer, there's
been actually quite a few
autoregressive language
models trained on the
same class of things.
And you can ask
questions like, what are
the different vocabulary sizes?
Or what kind of layer
norms do we use?
Or what kind of position
embeddings do people use?
And we see some
fairly clear trends.
I'll be talking
about this as we go.
So the goal here is that
we're going to cover
a couple of different things.
We're going to cover common
architecture variations.
So these are different building
blocks of the transformer.
And after we've established
what the standard building
blocks are, like, what do we
use for the nonlinearities?
Or what do we use for
position embeddings?
Then we're going to talk
about hyperparameters.
We're going to go
down even lower detail
and say, what is ff_dim?
Should we make that
a multiple of four
or multiply the hidden
by four to get ff_dim?
How many vocab
elements should I have?
And then after that,
we're going to talk
about very low-level
tricks of how
to get models to train stably.
And the reason why I'm going to
talk about that in this lecture
is because these
stability tricks
have a pretty close connection
with the architecture variation.
One of the things that higher
level I want to impress upon you
is that architectures are
actually a very complex set
of trade offs.
What does the
architecture have to do?
Well, it has to learn from
data, so it has to generalize.
It has to train
efficiently on GPUs.
And it has to not blow up.
Halfway through training,
if your training loss
is just go down like this
and then suddenly blow up,
that's no good at all.
So all these
different requirements
end up getting baked straight
into the architecture.
And that's why these
things are a little bit
messy and a little bit complex.
But you should
keep that in mind.
And that's why things are,
in many ways, not so elegant.
So we're going to start with
the core architecture piece.
And as a high-level
view, I think the way
that I see a lot of
the architecture stuff,
looking, basically,
historically,
is in the early days of starting
with a transformer until GPT-3
or so.
There's a lot of
experimentation that happens.
People try lots of
different things.
There's no gold standard
that everyone has unified on.
And then Llama 2 comes out.
And everyone's like,
wow, Llama 2 is great,
I want my own Llama 2.
And so everyone starts
training Llama 2 alikes
with minor variation
that people have.
And then finally, last year,
we saw really big differences
or a trend towards
architecture modifications
that make training more stable.
And this year, we
see lots of trends
towards architecture variations
that enable longer context
dependence.
So there are these big
themes that are happening.
But really, I think
you see this big point
when Llama 2 comes out,
and everyone's like, wow, I
want to train some of that.
And then suddenly, or not
suddenly, but after that,
people are starting
to explore once again.
So it's cool to see all of
these different changes.
OK.
I think people can disagree
about a lot of things
on architectures, but
there is one thing
that everyone agrees on.
If you take the transformer
paper, I think a lot of people
say like, the transformer
people got most of the things,
except this.
And the thing that they
really did not get right
or I think, most people
agree, they did not get right
is where you put the layer norm.
So in the original
transformer paper,
the layer norm goes in what you
would call the residual path.
So in the transformer, you
have the residual stream
that's x, that runs
through the whole network.
And then you are going
to be applying attention,
which does some computation.
And it will add back a delta
back into the residual stream.
And then, in order to make
sure that these gradients are
stable across
layers, a layer norm
is placed at the end of
each of these components.
Now, instead of
putting the layer norms
in the residual stream,
there's an alternative,
I'll refer to this as prenorm,
in which you can put the layer
norm outside of the
residual stream,
but before each of
the computations.
So you can put it before
the multihead attention,
you can put it before the FFN.
We'll call this prenorm.
The nomenclature will get
a little bit confusing.
You can call this
postnorm for now,
but let's call
this residual norm,
because you're putting the
norm in the residual layer.
Basically, all modern
language models
push the layer norm outside
of the residual stream.
This is just like a thing that
basically, everybody does.
There is one funny
exception, but it is OPT350M.
And if you all are familiar
with language models, we know,
OPT, in general, was a
mess of a language model.
And OPT 350M is even more so
because I don't why only that
model has a postlayer norm
in the residual stream.
OK.
So this is one of the things
that everyone agrees on.
And so you might wonder, why
is this such a unified thing
across all of the
different models?
And if you look at
some of the early work,
studying, where do you place the
layer norm style research, what
you really see is that the early
motivation for a lot of this
was, when you train
a transformer,
you need to do a warm up.
Actually, modern
transformer training
still does warm up as well.
But you definitely need to
do warm up when you train.
Now, wouldn't it be nice if
we could remove the warm up.
So that was the
initial motivation
for a lot of this research.
But people quickly realized
that removing the warm up
had very serious issues in terms
of the stability and convergence
of these things.
So if you did postnorm plus
layer norm, which is basically
the original transformer thing,
you got this purple dashed line,
oh, you just don't converge as
well compared to doing something
like prenorm, you can
ignore the other terms,
you would get much
nicer convergence
even without warm up.
So this was the
original motivation.
But really, what
people quickly realized
is that moving the layer norms
outside the residual stream
has some pretty
important implications
as you make your network deeper
and as you start to grapple
with stability issues.
To me, I think the
gradient attenuation
issues are the most clear.
When you talk to people
who do architecture design,
I'm not really one of the people
that deeply engages in this.
But one of the things
that people often say
is, keep your
residual stream clean.
So in this case,
you have your x's
coming in from the
on, the prenorm side.
And this x propagates all
the way up to the top,
all the way up to
your final output.
And that allows gradients to
propagate in the backward pass,
straight through this.
That makes gradient
propagation very simple,
which improves both stability
and signal propagation.
And that's what people
realized very, very quickly,
that if you do
something like prenorm
in blue at initialization, the
gradient sizes remains the same,
because you have this nice,
straight through propagation
in the backward pass.
On the other hand, if
you have post LayerNorm,
you have these
complicated effects
that happen, because your
LayerNorming, each time,
you're going through
a transformer block.
And that's going to change
the norm of your gradients
as you go backwards through.
So you can see,
from the principle
of keep your residual
stream clean,
that prenorm makes
a lot of sense.
People also realized
through experimentation
that this also improves
stability, in general,
that the sizes and
frequencies of gradient spikes
were improved under prenorm
compared to postnorm.
And this is a figure
from Salazar and Ngyuen,
who were one of
the first ones, I
think, to study this
phenomena carefully.
I think this is the reason
why it's stuck around.
Stability and the
ability to go deep
are both very, very important
for modern large language
models.
And so this idea of moving
your LayerNorm outside
of the residual stream is
one that basically everyone
has adopted.
So now, if putting LayerNorms
in residual streams is bad,
why does LayerNorm have
to be at the start?
Of course, we have prenorm,
which is before our computation.
But we could have it
after computation as well.
That's equally good, at
least under that logic.
And that's exactly right.
Many recent models, like
Grok, or Gemma 2, or OLMo 2,
have this structure where
they've moved the LayerNorm
after the computation.
So it's a postnorm
of a kind, but it's
outside the residual stream.
Other models still actually
just put LayerNorms everywhere.
They put a LayerNorm here.
They put a LayerNorm after.
I'll get to this later as
we talk about stability.
But one of the
other lessons that
seems to have held
up very well is,
if you have stability issues,
you can sprinkle in LayerNorms
everywhere.
And that will generally
improve stability.
It's almost very strange
to be saying this,
because it's so ridiculous.
And yet, that statement has
actually been proven right.
Every time people have
encountered stability issues,
they say, oh, but
what if we just throw
a LayerNorm into attention?
Turns out, that works too.
We'll get to that later.
OK, that's postnorm
or double norm,
in this case, where you
have two LayerNorms here.
OK.
The other thing that you can do
is, in the original transformer,
you have the layer norm, which
is this operation right here.
So you have your activations x,
you're going to mean subtract,
divide the variance, and
then scale it back up.
And this works just fine.
It's not like this is wrong.
And many models
have successfully
trained on this scheme.
But basically, most or all
modern models, I think,
use RMSNorm, which
doesn't subtract the mean
or add a bias term.
So it's just a scaling
down and scaling back up.
So you can see this
in the equation here.
And really, LayerNorm is
more expressive than RMSNorm.
So there's really
representationally
no reason why you
have to use RMSNorm.
But RMSNorm is nice,
because in practice, there's
really no expressiveness loss.
RMSNorm models just
as well as LayerNorm.
But more importantly,
it is faster.
This is the part where the
systems and architecture
codesign starts to come in.
Firstly mentioned in the
previous lecture, this idea
of arithmetic intensity.
We want to keep our
GPUs hot by doing
matrix multiplies and other
very intense computations.
We do not want to
be wasting our GPUs
by having them move little tiny
bits of memory back and forth.
That's a very inefficient
use of our very powerful GPU.
And so what we want is to
remove operations that are small
and involve memory
movement, but don't give us
much expressive power.
So by that view, what we
really want to be doing here
is, if the mean subtraction
and addition isn't really
doing much for us.
Just get rid of it.
You might think, OK,
why does this matter?
We're just optimizing
this teeny tiny operation
that accounts for, in
this case, something
like 0.17% of the total floating
point operations of our system.
But as Percy mentioned, it's
not really about the flops.
The flops are the floating
point operations we do,
that's multiplying matrices,
but that's not runtime.
Runtime is a much more
complicated object.
And statistical normalizations,
things like LayerNorm,
even though they're
only 0.17% of the flops,
depending on your workload
and depending on the setup,
can be up to 25% of the runtime.
That's crazy.
On tiny models, this can
be really, really big,
because you're still having to
move all these parameters back
and forth from fast to slow
memory and vice versa when
you're doing these operations.
So data movement is
really, really important.
And RMSNorm can still matter
a lot because of this.
So you can see the
difference here.
The arithmetic
intensity is in white.
And then you can see the
flops involved in black.
And you see that LayerNorm has
a very low arithmetic intensity,
which is the operation
we try to want
to remove as much as possible.
Yeah, question over there?
The movement for normalization
is so disproportionate
compared to density [INAUDIBLE].
So for something like
tensor contraction, which
is, in this case,
matrix multiplies,
the majority of the
workload is multiplying,
whereas for stat normalization,
the majority of the workload
is memory movement.
And memory movement
is quite slow.
So imagine the case, where
moving something is almost
all the compute.
Then you're still
paying quite a bit
here, because activations
can be quite large.
Yeah, I think the percent
runtime in this case
is quite extreme.
This is like in the tiny models
with matrices that don't really
generally make sense
in modern workloads,
but this is giving
you a sense of why
this is a free optimization.
And you do see this.
This is another
paper in which people
were evaluating different
architecture interventions,
Narang et al in 2020.
I think this was a Google paper.
And they show, for
teeny tiny transformer
of a 200 million parameters,
you get more steps per second.
That's the third column over
here when you switch to RMSNorm.
And in fact, you actually
get better performance, which
I don't think is something
that you're guaranteed,
but it's a nice
bonus, regardless.
So you get a free systems win
by just moving to RMSNorm.
And so basically,
everyone has decided
to move over to this now.
And in general, there's a
more general version of this.
There's no guarantee to any
of the things I'm saying.
But biased terms in
transformers and neural networks
are generally not that useful.
So in the original
transformer, the linear terms
all have biases, but most
implementations actually
just drop the biases entirely.
Once again, this is another
example of something
that's not very arithmetically
intense, but fairly memory
intensive, relatively speaking.
And so you might as
well just drop these
and get the free systems win.
There's also some
cases, I'll just
mention this offhand, where
the bias terms can also
induce stability issues, so
they're useful in other ways.
But really, I think the primary
reason these are dropped
is just to simplify things
from a systems perspective.
Cool.
OK.
So I think layer norms,
the story is pretty easy.
It's easy in the sense
that what people do
is fairly standardized.
Our understanding, not like
a deep theoretical level,
but our understanding of what
layer norm does is fairly good.
Everyone moves the layer norm
outside the residual stream,
often prenorm.
But I think this might partially
be because Llama 2 did that.
And we roughly
have a sense of how
to use LayerNorm to control
things like gradient spikes
and keep signal
propagation nice.
Related to that, we also now
basically always use RMSNorm.
And you hopefully understand
the general principles
here of basically, just
dropping bias terms.
And that allows us to keep
our system more arithmetically
intense while keeping the
expressive power the same.
I think the unsatisfying thing
about a lot of architectures
is that, you can't really
reason about this beforehand,
but we don't beforehand that
dropping the bias terms is OK.
But from a lot of
experimentation and now,
collectively acquired
knowledge, we
roughly that dropping the
bias terms on both the linear
and RMSNorm is OK for typical
language modeling workloads.
This is the kind of
statement that we
can make on the
basis of what we do
when we look at a variety
of different models.
Any questions for
LayerNorm stuff?
Good.
OK.
So now, I'm going to
talk about activations.
And there's a whole
zoo of activations.
There's just a lot--
ReLU, GeLU, Swish, ELU,
GeGLU, SeLU, SwiGLU, LiGLU.
And what are these things?
I think, at one point of
my more stats ML training,
I thought to myself, I will
never learn these things.
I will make it a point of pride
to never know what a SwiGLU is.
But now, it's actually
very important
for us to actually have
a general sense of what
these objects are and
which parts of these names
actually matter for performance.
So you can build and train
a language model on just
a fairly vanilla activation.
I guess, Chinchilla is
probably the best model
out of that group.
But even if you
just want a ReLU,
you can train a reasonably
performant language model
using just that activation.
There's nothing wrong with that.
And if we move to GeLU, which
is a Gaussian error unit,
and really, the only difference
is this tiny divot at the bottom
here, which really, for
the most of the activation
doesn't change
anything but changes
the gradients right near zero.
Then you can train
models like GPT 3.
That's a perfectly
good large language
model, not modern by modern
standards, but perfectly fine.
But then we get to the
gated linear units,
like SwiGLU and GeGLU.
And these are really where
most of the action is.
This is very similar
to LayerNorm in that,
I think almost all
credible modern language
models use a gated
linear unit of some kind.
OK.
So what is gated linear unit?
So these are gated activations.
So if we want to
look at something
like a feed forward
layer, we can just
look at this first part.
This is a very standard
ReLU feed forward.
I have my x.
I hit it with a W1.
I entrywise threshold at 0.
And then I hit it
with another W2.
I get my output right.
Very straightforward
ReLU network.
I don't say this as my
personal experience,
but another thing that is often
said in architecture design
is that gating is
often very helpful.
So if you apply that very
general heuristic, what
you might get is to
say, OK, well, instead
of just having this
entrywise ReLU,
why don't we also have a gate?
And the second gate,
the second term
here, this is just going to
multiply the output of my ReLU,
entrywise.
And I have a second
matrix V. OK.
Now, this is just going to
modulate the output of my ReLU.
And then I'm going to do
everything else the same.
So instead of just having
xW1, W2, I have xW1,
and I'm going to
gate that with xV.
This is another activation
the same size as this.
And then I'm going to down
project it back with W2.
OK.
So what is this?
Now, this is a ReGLU.
You make these names by
adding the first activation,
in this case, ReLU and GLU,
so the ReLU gated linear unit.
And gating has been a very
effective other primitive
in architecture design.
And it turns out that this
is very effective in language
modeling as well.
So if you take
something like a GeLU,
we've already talked about that.
That's the ReLU, but with a
little divot at the bottom
here, you will get a GeGLU.
And if you take a SwiGLU,
which is x times a sigmoid,
then you will get a SwiGLU.
So this is a squish
times the rest of it.
And this really covers a
lot of the modern models.
Generally, the Google
folks have used GeGLU,
so like the Gemma models,
the T5 models are those.
And everything that's a Llama
descendant uses a SwiGLU.
So PaLM and the
Llama descendants
are all SwiGLU models.
I would say that SwiGLU is
probably the more dominant one,
but honestly, amongst the gated
units, doesn't really matter.
Now, here's a side note that
will be a semi-important piece
of trivia later.
If you look up here,
you will notice
that there are more parameters
for the gated model, because I
have this parameter V. And so
if you do a little bit of math,
I now have three matrices
instead of two matrices.
What you should do is, you
should maybe use a smaller
feedforward dimension
by a factor of 2/3,
in order to keep the
parameter count the same.
So this is roughly
the idea of, well,
I want to keep the same
number of total parameters
as my original MLP, but I
now want to make it gated.
So I'm going to make the
feedforward dimension,
which is the output
dimension of this W,
a little bit smaller by 2/3.
So this is a general rule of
thumb that people have followed,
but it's not really
an iron rule.
The original Noam
Shazeer paper that
proposed this had some very
small deltas originally,
but they're consistent deltas.
And I think to his credit,
I think a lot of his papers
have these error bar assessments
of training multiple replicates
and checking to see
if they're better.
And if you look,
the GLU variants
are almost always consistently
better than the nonGLU variants.
And this is a parameter
matched comparison,
because Noam Shazeer is always
doing this 2/3 adjustment
to make sure that all of the
models have the same total
number of parameters.
So this is quite nice.
It's, in some ways, a free win.
Almost everyone uses a GLU.
There have been
other more controlled
systematic comparisons.
This is the same paper I
was talking about before,
Narang et al in 2020.
Google, actually, in the 2020s,
did quite a few nice large scale
architecture comparison papers,
although with a T5 architecture
and not an autoregressive
language model.
And they basically
comprehensively compare things
like GLU.
And you see, once
again, if we look
at the SwiGLU, or the GeGLU,
or the GLUs in general,
they do significantly
better at loss
or the other downstream metrics.
Fairly compelling on these
papers, also clear from now
a lot of model training runs
that SwiGLU and GLU are good.
So there's a lot of
variations in gating,
but really, the important
single axis to know
is that gating for these
nonlinearities is actually
quite important, gives you
a nice boost without much
of a computational cost.
That's not to say that gated
linear units are necessary.
I mean, GPT 3 was that--
I think, the Nemotron 340B
model used a Squared ReLU,
which is a crazy choice,
but that works too.
Both of these models are
perfectly performant,
but it's actually quite rare
to see anything that's not
trained on a gated linear unit.
So evidence is pointing
towards consistent gains
on using these gating tricks.
So those are, I think, the more
consensus choices for things
that we can do in architecture.
Now, this one, I think,
is a really fun idea,
but one that, I think, now, the
test of time has shown maybe
is not quite as good or maybe
not as popular of an idea.
Normally, we do our
transformer blocks serially.
We compute our attention,
then we compute
the MLP, one after the other.
If you're very
systems-minded, you
might say, well, this
introduces a bottleneck.
I have to wait for
the computation of one
to do the other.
If they were,
instead, in parallel,
I could bring to bear
some new and cool systems
optimizations, potentially.
So you might ask, could we
parallelize the transformer
block?
And this was
originally an idea that
was in GPTJ, which is
an open source attempted
replication of GPT 3.
And very interestingly,
I think GPTJ
has been surprisingly
influential in propagating
a lot of ideas.
I mean, PaLM as well.
Google is actually surprisingly
bold with the architectures
that they do.
But the description
in PaLM, which
you can see in their
report, is the following--
instead of nesting
this, which is
the sequential firm
at the top, you're
just going to add
together the output
of the MLP and the
attention layer
and just add both of those
back into the residual stream.
If you implement this
right, you can actually
share a lot of the components.
You can share the LayerNorms.
You can fuse the
matrix multiplies.
This allows you to potentially
get additional systems
optimizations.
And I think a lot
of the people that
have been influenced by Google.
So Cohere, I know,
was founded from one
of the former
transformer authors.
They do a lot of
Google-inspired optimizations.
They followed this architecture,
but not very many others.
This has been an approach
that has really fallen out
of popularity over the
past, I think, two years,
I think mainly because
optimization of the serial form
has gotten sufficiently
good that the system's
gains from the
second one just isn't
worth the small hits
to representation power
that you end up getting,
going from parallel to serial.
Effectively, you
can think about it,
as you've lost
half of your depth.
And that can be a deleterious
thing to do to your model.
So in terms of the
architecture things, actually,
the fact that this is so
short should suggest to you
how much the original
transformer formulation has
somewhat stood the test of
time, because the only thing I'm
really talking about changing
here is where the norms go,
or whether we have bias terms,
or whether we get the MLPs.
But those are actually
pretty minor changes
compared to all the
things that you can do.
Now, those of you that are
carefully paying attention
might say, but wait, there's a
lot of transformer alternatives
that change the attention.
Yes, you'll have to wait until
next lecture, because today,
I'm just only going to cover
core attention-based methods.
And next lecture, I'll throw
in a little bit of state space
model stuff.
But as long as you're in this
dense attention land, actually,
the architecture from the
original transformer paper
is pretty close to what we do.
So you see quite a bit of this.
So just now going back to
this, blue here is RMSNorm,
black is LayerNorm.
You see most of
the modern models
are RMSNorm models, serial
versus parallel layers.
The blue one is parallel,
the rest is serial.
You see mostly serial layers,
prenorm versus postnorm.
Some of these ones that
I marked as postnorm
are actually pre and postnorm.
And then these ones
on the right, these
are GLUs, almost always,
with the exception
of things like Falcon, which
use a gated linear unit.
But almost all of
these are really
gated linear units
for modern models.
So you can see the
trends quite visually
from what I'm telling you.
OK.
So really, the
thing that is very
different across
implementations,
and I think a place where a
lot of the architecture stuff
is still in flux is how
you do position dependence
and incorporate information
from other positions.
So the core attention
component, in some sense.
So there are lots
of different ways
that you can encode
position into a transformer.
And just to remind
you right, this
is very, very important,
because attention
is positionally independent.
They're just inner products,
so you can just shuffle them.
And attention would be the same
if you don't have a position
embedding.
The original transformer had
sine and cosine embeddings,
a Fourier transform
intuition that if you
have sines and cosines, then
you can recover position
from that, no matter what.
A number of other large models
that followed soon after that
used absolute embeddings,
where each position had
its own different embedding.
And then several
other Google models
like to use relative embeddings.
And here, you're not adding
embeddings into the word vector
embeddings, but instead, you're
adding a vector to the attention
computation itself.
So if you're three
positions off,
the attention matrix gets a
different offset added to it.
And models like T5 and
Chinchilla use this scheme.
The thing that has really
become pretty dominant
in terms of position
embedding is this class
of embeddings called
RoPE, which some of you
may be familiar with.
Most models past 2024 use
this type of embedding.
And it's remarkable, given
that RoPE, in some ways,
came out of nowhere.
Originally, I think this was
also a GPTJ innovation from,
I think, not very well-known
blog post and paper combination
from an author in China.
But really, it has some
really interesting ideas
for why you would do
something like RoPE.
So RoPE is a relative
position embedding.
And a relative
position embedding,
let's make an opinionated
stance that I should not
care about the absolute
position of any words.
So if you A and apple
appear together,
even if it appears at
the start or at the end,
in RoPE embeddings, they
should get the same result.
And we want to represent
it in this way.
So I have an embedding f, and
I have another embedding f.
And these are going to take
in the identity of the words x
and y and the positions
absolute of i and j.
And I want this to be equal.
If I take the inner
product of these embeddings
to be equal to a
function, that only
depends on the
relative difference.
And every existing
embedding before it
didn't really fulfill
this equality.
Sine is not relative, because it
has these absolute cross terms
that are not relative.
Absolute position embeddings,
just by the name of it,
is obviously not relative.
And then relative embeddings,
technically, these are relative,
but they're not embeddings,
because they're just
adding to the attention matrix.
So there's no inner
product structure
that you can extract
out of this guy.
So given this, you
might ask, is there
a nice way that we can truly
have this relative embedding?
And the idea is very cool.
It's really just looking
at other properties
about angles and cosines.
So we want our embeddings to be
invariant to absolute positions.
And we know that inner
products of any kind
are invariant to
arbitrary rotation.
So the idea is to say, I'm
going to take my semantic word
vectors, the ones that are
independent of any position.
So this is my starting point.
And then I'm going to rotate
each of these vectors,
in this case, in 2D, based on
the position that the words
appear.
So just as a simple example,
let's say we have the sentence,
"We know that."
"We" appears as at position 0,
so I'm not going to touch that
at all.
I'm just going to
keep that where it is.
The word "no" is at position
1, so I'm going to rotate it
by some angle.
And that's my one
position rotation.
Now, what happens if
I apply the same idea
to the following sequence?
Of course, we know.
In this case, "we" and
"no" are still adjacent.
They're right next
to each other,
but their absolute
position has shifted.
"Of course" comes
before "we know now."
In this case, I'm going
to rotate the word "we"
by two positions, because
it's two index, 0, 1, 2.
So the word "we" is in the
second position number 2,
so I rotate by two.
I rotate "no" by
three positions,
because it's in
position number 3.
And what do you know the
relative angle between these two
is still separated by 1.
So this is a very, very simple
idea of just using rotations
to represent position.
And if we do that, then anytime
we take an inner product,
those inner products are
going to be invariant
of absolute positions.
Now, you might say, well,
in two dimensions, that's
pretty easy, because you've
only really got one choice,
you've got clockwise
and counterclockwise.
But in high dimensions, there's
an infinite space of ways
that you can rotate vectors.
So what do you do
in D dimensions?
Well, you do the simplest
possible thing, and it works.
The simplest possible thing
is to reduce it to the 3D case
repeatedly.
So you have a D
dimensional vector.
Just cut it up
into chunks of two.
And each pair of two
dimensions gets rotated.
And the theta at which
these things rotate vary.
Some of them are
very low frequency,
so they rotate very
slowly, so they can
capture long range dependence.
Some of them rotate
very quickly,
so they capture things like, are
they neighbors to each other?
And then at the end, after I've
rotated every pair of vectors,
I get my final embedding.
So this is the RoPE approach.
The paper, if you read it,
has a very complex motivation
about complex
numbers, but really, I
think the intuitive way, at
least to me to think about it,
is to just, you want
to rotate by reducing
to the two-dimensional case,
and you're just rotating
every pair of coordinates.
Gemma 4 just came
out on Thursday.
And they have another
different kind of fun thing
that they do, which
they call, I think,
proportional RoPE or p-RoPE,
which is a really strange way
to just say that the only thing
they rotate is the first two
coordinates, but that's
another valid thing that you
can do as well.
So there's a lot
of different things
that you can do in this
space that end up working.
OK.
In practice, what you're
going to end up doing is,
you can take your
vector, and you
can make a sparse multiply
with sines and cosines.
And this is going to be giving
you some way of rotating
your input vectors x's.
So x times w times r, this is
going to be your final embedding
that you get.
And finally, this is
a sine and cosine,
which looks a little
like sine embeddings.
But it's really important that
I'm multiplying with these sines
and cosines rather than
using them as embeddings,
because that means that
there are no cross terms.
And this is purely relative.
There's no absolute
position information
that you'll get out
of inner products.
If we really, really wanted
to get into low-level details,
and you ask, how do I
actually implement this thing?
You're going to have to do that.
You have your usual
attention stuff.
And then what you do is you
generate cosine and sine angles
based on the position IDs
of where your sequence is.
And then you're going
to apply those cosines
and sines onto both your queries
and keys for your attention
computation.
And you can either apply
them as a matrix multiply,
or you can go through
and apply them manually,
just as a rotation.
Fairly straightforward.
And you would do this
at the attention level
rather than at the
very bottom, to enforce
position invariance,
every time you're
doing attention computations.
So that was RoPE.
It is a little bit confusing,
but once you understand
the geometry of just
rotating things,
it's actually fairly
straightforward.
OK.
I'm going to pause
here for one moment,
in case anyone has questions
about the various architecture
bits.
We're going to then talk
about even lower level details
about hyperparameters, so yes.
Do you know of any papers
that do a higher dimensional?
Higher dimensional rotation.
It's a good question.
I don't think so.
But a higher
dimensional rotation,
like any 2D rotation in the
space would just be a variant
of this.
You could certainly do any one
manifold that is a closed loop.
I have not seen that.
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE] What do you
think is the best way
to distill this
kind of knowledge
from papers and
technical reports?
It's a good question.
I don't know if there's a
way beyond some combination
of looking broadly enough
to get a pattern, which
is what the procedure I'm trying
to do in this lecture here.
And then the other one is to try
it yourself, even a much smaller
scale, to form an intuition in a
theory for how these things come
together.
I think those two are
really the right ways.
I think reading any
single paper in isolation
is very, very difficult,
especially now,
because no single paper seems to
give any full detail for a lot
of language models these days.
Oh, lots of questions now.
OK, good.
We'll go in.
Yeah.
So I have a question
on the parallel layers
and [INAUDIBLE] layers.
Yeah, I understand,
the modern models
are thinking of the
resource efficiency,
so they use the parallel layers.
But there's a difference between
accuracy for these two patterns.
I want to know what's
the degree of accuracy.
Is it big enough or
also small enough
to allow the current
model trainers
to ignore that, or [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, I think that's
actually really mixed.
So if you read the
original PaLM paper,
I think they're very
confident about the use
of parallel layers, like no
performance drop, 15% systems
utilization improvement.
So if you read just that, you'll
say, oh, it's just as good.
But I think a lot of
the later Google models
have stopped using this,
which you can take on
as an implicit signal
that actually, there
might be some losses.
And once again, this
one is a little bit hard
to get precise numbers
on, because no one's
done the ablations,
as far as I know
on parallel versus serial,
controlled nice ablations,
at least.
Yeah.
What's the difference between
P-RoPE and RoPE if you
might have read [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah.
I mean, this difference
is really just,
which of the
coordinates you rotate?
You don't rotate most of
them, because a lot of the--
I mean, the argument
originally, I think,
is that the low frequency parts
just aren't rotating very much.
And so you can drop them
if you're really strapped
for of extra space.
And this is really
an optimization
for teeny tiny models, where
you don't have very much hidden
dimensions to have
activations for.
Yeah.
So the relative embeddings,
not having an inner product.
Is that because it only
applies to keys basically?
I was trying to understand.
Yeah.
So they applied both
to the keys and values,
which is why you get this
relative effect from where
you are.
You want to not
have cross terms.
So if you look at the sine
and cosine embeddings,
then you'll not only get
the original vectors,
you'll get these weird cross
terms between the position
embeddings and the word
embedding themselves,
and so on and so forth.
And then you can back out
what the absolute position is.
So even sine and
cosine embeddings
are not like pure relative
position embeddings.
You have to accept the premise
that the relative embedding is
what you want.
But once you do, you end
up at the RoPE solution
somewhat naturally.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, Yeah.
So what's the issue?
So the issue with this
is that it just can't
be factorized as a product.
That's more of an
aesthetic problem.
If your constraints are,
I need it to be relative,
and I need it to factorize
as f of xi and f of yj,
then this is not a
solution in that class.
To be fair, there's
a lot of embeddings
that work this way that
do work, like l of i
and other kinds of approaches do
this inject into the attention
matrix.
And they do reasonably well.
It's not necessarily
the one that's
become the dominant
approach, is what I can say.
Cool.
OK.
Great.
Now, we'll talk about
hyperparameters.
And I think hyperparameters
are really something
that you start to engage
with once you actually
have to train a model.
When your knowledge about
language models are abstract,
you don't have to care
about any of these.
But once you have
to instantiate it,
you start to ask
questions like, well,
how big should the
feedforward size be?
How many heads should I have?
What should my vocab size be?
And you might also
have questions
of, what should my weight
decay or dropout be?
Do I even need to regularize?
I have a lot of tokens.
So do I need regularization?
And do I need very deep
models or very wide models?
What are the right kinds
of things to do here?
And all of these, if you
start out with no knowledge,
it's actually very
daunting, because you
have to search this very
big high-dimensional space.
But the space of
things that people try
is actually pretty small.
And from that,
maybe you can start
to think about smarter
search processes of where
you want to vary things.
One of the things that's a
really consensus hyperparameter
is this idea of the ratio
between the feedforward size,
which is the output
of your first matrix
multiply in an MLP and
the model dimension.
So this is really the ratio of
the two dimensions of your W1
as well your W2 matrix.
This seems like a thing
that's very important
and controls the
richness of your MLPs.
So what should it be?
Well, for whatever
reason, it should maybe
be four times your
hidden dimension.
And this is a rule of thumb
that works remarkably well.
And I will show you some data on
why maybe this is a fine number
to choose.
There's a few exceptions.
And funnily enough, the
really extreme exceptions
backtrack on that.
OK.
Exception number 1 is variance
of the gated linear unit.
I already told you about this.
So if you were
thinking about it,
this is probably cached
in your head right.
GLUs have more parameters if
you keep the same dimensions.
So if you want to keep the
parameter size of your MLPs
the same, well, you need
to scale down by 2/3.
So most GLU variants, this means
that you're going to end up with
something like 2.67-ish.
So everyone that's
down here, 2.67 to 2.5,
this is roughly applying
this 2/3 correction.
And then for whatever reason,
the Llama 2 folks decided,
well, we actually have very
efficient attention heads
with MQA, which I'll
talk about later.
And because of that, we
can multiply this ratio
by an arbitrary 1.33.
And we'll get roughly 3.5.
And so the Llama
people arbitrarily
chose a slightly
different ratio,
which essentially emphasizes
the MLPs a little bit more.
But really, if you actually
look through all the papers,
you'll find either
2.6-ish or 3.5 for GLUs,
or 4 if you're doing
non-GLU models.
OK.
There's another
exception, which I
find to be very funny,
but also very, very cool,
which is, throughout, as you
read these technical reports,
you'll find that
most people are just
very boring in their
choice of architectures.
They're like, we did Llama,
but we changed one thing.
But folks at Google are
very bold, sometimes.
And T5 is one of
my favorite ones,
because they have some
really bold settings.
They decided that instead of
following this 4x rule of thumb,
they decided that they want
to have a 64x multiplier,
which is way bigger than 4.
And they have a
reasonable argument
for this as well, this another
systems-based argument.
They said, well, the bigger
my matrix multiplies,
the more efficient I
can keep my hardware.
So if I make this
multiplier really big,
then my matrix multiplies
can potentially
be more efficiently utilized.
And some others, like
Gemma 2, have also
tried to really push a
little bit higher on this.
But really, T5 is
astounding exception at 64.
I don't think any
other model has really
gone that high in the
feed forward multiplier.
And empirically, if you
look at other works that
try to do more controlled
comparisons of this ratio,
I've taken this one
from Kaplan in 2020.
This is the classic
neural scaling loss
paper, where they do various
controlled studies on language
models.
You'll see, this wasn't
the point of the study.
It was a scaling law study.
But you'll see in
one of the panels
that they actually have ablation
or sweep, where they change
the feed forward ratio,
and they look at the loss
for a very small model here.
But what they find
in this paper is,
there's a basin, where
you start at about one,
and you end about
maybe 10, where
this hyperparameter is pretty
good and very, very flat.
You lose very little relative
to the optimal loss down here.
And then if you get it really
wrong, you get above 10 to 100
or something like
that, then your loss
starts really shooting
up quadratically.
And so a lot of these choices
that range between 2.6 to 4,
they're all falling into
this relatively nice basin,
so you're fine choosing
those numbers right.
So what can we learn
about this hyperparameter?
Well, the default choices
have worked very well
for nearly all modern
language models.
So you can safely choose that.
T5 was a fine model or the
version 1 T5 was a fine model.
It wasn't a bad model.
And so even radical choices
can technically work,
but it's probably going
to be compute-inefficient.
And I think the funniest
part of this saga,
this is the punchline
of the T5 saga to me,
is that they have a follow up
model T5 v1.1 that's supposed
to be the improved
version of T5.
And they go back to the
standard 2.5 multiplier.
So there's nothing
explicitly stated here.
But clearly, when they
tried to update T5,
they decided that
they wanted to go back
to a more standard
multiplier, which I
find to be a little bit funny.
So that's the feed forward
ratio, which now, you
have a rough sense of what the
right order of magnitude is.
Now, let's talk about
a different consensus
hyperparameter.
I always found this to be very
strange when teaching 224n
and just teaching students
about this, which is,
if you have a
multihead attention,
where you have multiple
heads for your attention
in your transformer, the
canonical thing to do,
the thing that almost
everyone does is,
if you have multiple heads, you
make sure that the size of those
heads, the head dimension is
such that you have the same
dimension as a single
head transformer.
So you always make sure that
you divide the hidden dimension
to basically, multiply with h.
So in this case, you have
h the number of heads,
and the dimension of
each head is d over h.
So you multiply the
two and you get d.
For some reason, this
is the rule of thumb.
Of course, this doesn't
have to be true.
We can arbitrarily change the
ratios between head dimensions
and model dimensions.
But most models do
follow this guideline.
And it turns out to
work pretty well.
And we can look at a variety
of different models, classic
and new.
I have the latest and
greatest coin as well.
And you find, yeah, the ratios
are roughly around one a model
head, notable exception of
T5 and even lambda, which
is another Google model.
But really, everyone
sticks around one.
And I think this is
an interesting one.
I think the thing about
head dimensions that I'll
end with here is,
I think this is yet
another forgiving
hyperparameter.
There's a couple ablations
that people have done.
There's, once again, a
pretty wide basin around one
that you can get away with.
But that one's maybe not the
most critical hyperparameter.
I think maybe one of the most
critical and interesting ones,
I think, conceptually, is
this idea of an aspect ratio.
And to add an extra point
here, when you scale models
up or down, the
way you usually do
that is you fix an aspect
ratio, like how wide your model
is versus how deep it is.
And then you make
the model bigger.
So the aspect ratio,
in some sense,
controls the entire
depth to width trade off
as you make models bigger.
Now, you might wonder how
deep should my model be.
If you've been following
all this stuff on reasoning
and so on, you
might think I need
a really deep model or
really shallow model
if I want systems utilization.
You might think that
there's a lot of variation.
And there is a lot of
variation, much more so
than other hyperparameters.
But there's actually a
fairly clear sweet spot
that most modern
models fall into.
You don't really see
models go too deep.
And you also don't see models
go too wide in either direction.
You see, most models have a
ratio of about 100 D model
over n layers.
So about 100s width for
every layer that you have.
I mean, this is true
for GPT 3, or Llama,
or any one of these models.
And really, I think the
considerations are partly
a trade off between
expressiveness and hardware.
If you have an
extremely deep model,
they get very, very annoying
to deal with, systems-wise.
The deeper your model,
what is the ways that you
have for parallelizing them?
Well, you might have
to cut up your layers.
If you cut up your layers, we'll
talk about this in the systems
lecture.
Once you start cutting up
your layers depth-wise,
you have very serious
issues in parallelization.
Pipeline parallel, which
is what this is called,
is something that most
people really, really
do not want to deal with.
Whereas width is much
easier to parallelize.
If you have a really wide model,
you can cut that up very easily
in your GPUs.
Tensor parallel is
what it's called.
It's much, much
simpler to deal with.
And so in some sense, there
are systems reasons to go wide.
And maybe there's expressiveness
reasons to go deep.
And you end up at roughly 100.
And I think one of the
really interesting things
about transformer
hyperparameters
is, there are a lot
of hyperparameters
that seem quite important, but
they're also fairly forgiving.
And people have converged
roughly on the minimum.
This is yet another
plot from Kaplan,
et al, which shows another
sweep over hyperparameters
for differently sized models.
And once again,
you see, regardless
of the size of your
model, roughly speaking,
the optimum aspect
ratio is fairly similar,
and they live at about hundreds,
maybe a little bit less,
depending on how you want
to do the accounting.
But really, anywhere near
100 is a pretty safe bet
for aspect ratios
EK and others did a number of
really interesting architecture
variation experiments, in which
their general conclusion on this
was that, let's look
at the top panel here,
you have a lot of
different kinds of models
that you can have in terms
of depth to width trade offs.
But as you sweep the
depth to width trade offs,
you find that really, the
only thing that matters,
in some sense, is flops.
As you increase the flops,
the models get better.
And that's really controlling
the majority of the effects, not
necessarily the aspect ratio.
And so I think what has
really emerged from this
is the sense that there's
a general forgiving band
of hyperparameters that
people tend to choose.
And then you really worry
about primarily, your system's
utilization rather than
expressiveness concerns,
which are hard to reason about.
Cool.
And then maybe the last
hyperparameter thing
that I want to mention
is vocabulary sizes.
And this one's
interesting to me,
because there's a
really clear difference
between two classes of models.
I think, in the early days of
open source model training,
there were a lot of
monolingual models,
whose only goal was
to be good on English.
And for those models, you had
these much smaller vocab sizes,
in the 30,000 range.
And then post Llama,
a lot of people
were really interested in
multilingual or production
systems, these include closed
source models like GPT 4.
All of these have much,
much larger vocab sizes.
And these are roughly in the
100,000 to 200,000 vocab range.
And you see, generally,
that Google models
have a ton more vocab.
Llama derivatives roughly
range at about 100,000 tokens.
And then the monolingual
models are about 30,000.
This is somewhat clear.
The multilingual models really
do need much larger vocab
to cover the whole space.
Generally, the models on
the right are also bigger.
There have been
scaling law studies,
showing that the bigger your
model, the larger the vocab
it can handle.
And so this is also
partially driven
by modern scaling trends,
where the models on the right
are generally bigger.
No ones training large
monolingual models anymore.
So yeah.
[INAUDIBLE] the style stuff.
How to use those vocab sizes?
Sorry, the question was, if you
have multilingual models or--
Multimodal.
Yeah.
So I guess, it
depends on the way
that your tokens are encoded.
But if you're tokenizing your
images and things like that,
then you need to have many more
tokens to account for those.
If you look at various
open source releases,
they'll have a different
image tokenizer
with its own vocab,
which is quite large.
Yeah.
How valid is it to
compare, I suppose,
this provides for
different [INAUDIBLE]?
How valid is it to compare bits?
Oh, that is a great question.
OK.
Yeah.
That's not a
hyperparameter question,
but that's a good question.
So what is the right way?
So let me step back a moment
and put us in the right mindset.
So if we think about
language modeling,
language modeling is a
generative modeling task.
We are modeling the
probability of a sequence.
Now, as long as your
sequence is fixed,
you have adulterated it anyway.
And you provide a
probability over all strings,
that's always valid to compare.
At that level of
things is always valid.
Now, when you ask
the question, is
it valid to compare
the bits per byte
of two arbitrary tokenizers?
Really, there's
two things at play.
The one thing is, did you
touch the sequence at all?
If you look at some
tokenizers in the past
before subword tokenizers,
they would drop some tokens
or drop some words.
That makes the
comparisons invalid.
But modern tokenizers
are complete.
They can model any sequence,
so that's not a concern.
The other thing that
you have to worry about
is, are we length
normalizing in any way?
But for bits per
byte, you're always
normalizing with
the same number,
which is the number of bytes.
And so this is always
a valid comparison.
So that's how to think
about tokenizer comparisons.
So for example, I
think there have
been results showing that
comparing perplexity for a fixed
tokenizers always leads to
better downstream performance
on downstream tasks, as the same
thing improving for [INAUDIBLE].
Perplexity and BPP are
dual to each other.
So yes, if that's
what you're asking.
It's only yes and it's only no,
because if you're comparing--
you could train compared to
perplexity as [INAUDIBLE],
but you're changing
a different thing.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
We'll have to talk
later, because I'm not
sure I understand the question.
But I think that's an
interesting set of questions.
OK, good.
OK.
All right.
So we're going through, really,
the lowest levels of details
of language modeling,
which I think
really exposes a lot
of interesting ideas
while we talk through this.
And I think dropout is one
of the end regularization.
I think it's another very
interesting class of ideas,
also one that I think
is very counterintuitive
from your Machine
Learning 101 intuition.
So let's go through what I
think is the standard argument
for regularization.
Well, if I'm doing language
modeling, I have a lot of data.
I have more data than I can
process most of the time.
Unless you're at
Google, maybe even then,
There is more internet
data than there is flops.
So I'm probably not even going
to see the same data twice.
So I'm only going to do a
single pass on a corpus.
And there's very good
reasons and arguments
to believe that a single pass
of SGD or other optimizers
is never really going to
memorize my data very much.
So this means overfitting
is not really a problem,
almost ever during compute
constrained language modeling.
Now, some people even actually
only look at training loss,
because they believe so strongly
that overfitting doesn't
happen in single pass SGD.
Now, given this, you can
sit and think about this.
Should I use dropout
or weight decay
in language model training?
You can think about it a bit.
One unfortunate thing is
that a lot of recent models
don't talk about
this stuff at all.
It's really lower level
details than tech reports
are willing to expose.
But if you look, actually,
you find a lot of models
do both, especially
weight decay actually
is a fairly popular
intervention even
for modern high-performance
language models.
This is very, very surprising.
I mean, some of
the dropout things
maybe have gone out of favor,
but weightdecay actually remains
fairly popular.
And this is very mystifying.
Why is this?
And this is one
of the reasons why
I think deep learning is hard.
And this architecture lecture
is very strange and hard.
It's because these things
interact in very strange ways.
So there have been papers
that have argued and shown
nice evidence that
weight decay is actually
not a regularizer, sometimes.
It actually interacts with the
optimizer to essentially make
optimization better.
So if you look at the
training versus validation
loss across different
weight decay settings
on language model training
for single pass SGD,
you don't really
see any difference.
Weight decay isn't
shifting things,
so the validation
loss is better.
There's already no overfitting.
Run the x equals y line here.
So doesn't control
overfitting, but if we
look at different
levels of weight decay,
and not only just different
we look at weight decay combined
with learning rate decay.
What we find is that the
stronger weight decay runs,
these blue dashed
lines on the bottom
do significantly better,
because they start out slow,
but they essentially
end up converging
to a much better minimum later.
And this is generally true
when we decay learning rate,
not necessarily true when we're
in constant learning rate, which
is maybe somewhat more of where
your intuition is coming from.
So this is part of why it's
very difficult to reason,
a priori or from scratch,
the behavior of all
these different
choices and why I
think Percy and I have designed
this class, so that you interact
with stuff, because you
might come upon this thing
where basically, weight decay
is actually an optimization
intervention and not necessarily
a regularization intervention,
which is what you
would expect here.
So always keep that in
mind that these kinds
of unexpected effects
can really start to kick
in for these kinds of settings.
Cool.
All right.
So to put everything
together for hyperparameters,
there's actually, for a lot of
the maybe more hairy looking
hyperparameters, actually just
fairly standard choices that
have worked well for everybody.
Factor of 4 rule of
thumb, keep your head dim
and your number of heads
equal to the model dimension.
Pick an aspect ratio,
roughly around 100.
And if you ask about
regularization,
you want to maybe try
a couple of things,
because regularization
actually does interact
with optimizers in ways that
are quite counterintuitive.
So this is the thing that
some people still do,
even though you don't need
the regularization at all.
Actually, maybe I'll
stop here, in case.
Yeah.
Are there any significant
architectural differences maybe
for diffusion model?
Diffusions.
That, I have not looked
into enough, to be honest.
There aren't that
many people training.
Big diffusion is one issue.
And many of the models that have
been trained are retrofitted.
So I think the
architectures are actually
the same as a Llama-like model.
But if you're asking
the question, what's
the optimal architecture if
you were to train from scratch,
I don't know what
that is, actually,
off the top of my head.
Yeah.
Do you have any explanation
for why regularization mostly
affects [INAUDIBLE]?
Well, I guess, it's not that
regularization, in general,
affects optimization.
I don't think people
do dropout anymore,
because it doesn't really
interact well with optimization.
But for example, weight decay,
which is shrinkage to 0,
that might allow you to
use a higher learning rate,
or it might allow
you to decay faster.
There are lots of ways in
which all of these terms
are interrelated.
Cool.
OK.
Now, I've talked a lot about
how to design expressive models
by looking at all these other
models that have been trained.
One of the things that
I'll highlight now
is, over the last few
years, a really big emphasis
has not been on
performance alone,
it has actually
been on stability.
And this becomes an
increasingly important concern
as your models get more and
more expensive to train.
We've seen that a lot of
these choices are forgiving.
Everyone's doing similar stuff.
And so you can mess with
these, but you're not
going to get a big
performance difference.
That's fine.
But if your model suddenly blows
up some part into training,
you get these horrible-looking
spikes all over the place,
you might end up with a
model that is actually
not very good quality.
Or it might be unrecoverable.
You might have spent millions
of dollars in training.
And you get to a point
where the model is no longer
able to be trained any further.
That would be a
horrible thing to happen
if you have a lot of compute
that you want to spend.
So you don't want
to train models
that look like this blue
curve with spikes everywhere
and these big gradient
norms happening.
So what do we do to fix
these stability issues?
I mean, this is really, I
would say, a core, core issue.
And if you have stability
issues in language models,
or in general, neural
networks, there's
a few usual suspects that
you've got to start looking at.
One of them is the softmaxes.
And the softmax has two things
that are both really bad
for stability-- one of
them is an exponential.
You can see how that
blows up very quickly.
You also divide two numbers.
And that's also a potentially
very dangerous operation.
So softmax is one place
where you got to be extra,
extra careful.
And where are the softmaxes
in a language model?
Well, there's two of them.
There's one on the output side,
when we output our probability
distribution.
And then in attention, when
we normalize the attention,
there's going to
be another softmax.
So we can think of
both of those as really
danger zones for our model,
especially the attention.
Let's start with thinking
about the output softmax.
The output softmax
can blow up on us.
And one of the
things that we can do
is, we can try to control
the normalizer problem.
So let's think about
the softmax calculation.
We want to compute a log
probability to compute the loss.
Now, what is the
log probability?
Well, it's the output
of your model u.
And then you've got
this log normalizer.
This u is well-behaved,
because in some sense,
this is the output
of your model.
This is just the output of
your residual stream with all
the things that are added in.
So if u is well-behaved,
then the first term
is well-behaved, if
the model is being OK.
Now, the second term, this log
z, this might not be so OK.
If z is really big
or really small,
even if the output of your
model is somewhat well-behaved,
it could blow up.
And what is z?
Well, it's an exponential.
So it could potentially
blow up very quickly on you.
Or if this is 0, it could
also blow up on you.
So both of those directions
are very, very bad.
Now, we would ideally like
our z to be somewhere near 1
or log z to be somewhere near 0.
What can we do?
Well, one of the
things that you notice,
if you thought about the
action of the softmax,
is, this whole thing
is overparametrized.
I could push things in and out,
so if I add a constant to you,
I can manipulate the z's
without really affecting
the output of the softmax.
It can cancel out
between the normalizer
and the output of my model.
So because of that property,
one thing that I could do
is I could add a regularizer.
This is from Jacob Devlin's
paper, 2024-- sorry, 2014,
in which he adds this
squared log z term.
And what this is doing is
it's just penalizing how far
away your log z is from 0.
And if log z is
near 0, that's nice,
because this whole expression
is numerically stable.
This is called the z loss trick.
It's been used by
a number of papers.
Jacob Devlin and others
initially pioneered this back
in 2014.
And then it's become popular
again through a number
of open source models.
Baichuan, I think, was the first
open source model to do it,
but then DCLM and
OLMo, and others
have been using this trick
to stabilize their output
softmaxes.
So this is a surprisingly
effective thing.
So let's say, we've handled
the instability issues
on the output softmax.
Now, we have to
turn our attention
towards the other potential
problem, which is attention.
And this is a place where
lots of degeneracies happen.
Lots of techniques
have been developed
to control the instability that
attention operations generate.
And really, the high
level thing that I'll say
is, if you have
instability, if you
can throw a layer norm in there,
somehow, it might control it.
And that's really,
in some sense,
the design philosophy behind
this idea called the QK norm.
So what you do is remember
that we have our Qs and Ks that
are going to be
multiplied together,
and then they're going
to go into the softmax.
So in the standard
attention operation,
I'm going to layer norm
as a prelayer norm,
multiply with a QKV.
And I'm going to
get my Qs and Ks.
Those will get multiplied
by a matrix multiply,
I'll softmax them, and
I'll multiply that with a V
to get the weighted average.
And then I'll output
whatever comes after right.
So this is our usual attention.
Now, what happens if we
just throw in a LayerNorm
before we multiply
the Qs and Ks?
If we do that, then that the
inputs to this matrix multiply
and therefore, the inputs
to the softmax, roughly
have the same scale.
They're always going to
have a scale of roughly one,
because we've used the RMSE norm
to divide the size of those Qs
and Ks.
If we do that, then
we're going to keep
this softmax operation stable.
Tons of different
models do this.
It's originally from
the multimodal world.
Some folks who were
making multimodal models
initially discovered QK norm,
Idefcs, and Chameleon really
use this and proved it out.
And then a number of other
open source language models
realize that the same
tricks are entirely
applicable to stabilizing
attention for language models.
And I think this is now
very, very standard.
QK norm is actually a
very standard intervention
that most of the large
models now introduce.
It doesn't seem to
affect performance
from lots of different
training runs,
but it does definitely
prevent the kinds
of attention degeneracies.
And really, the way
that I've seen this is,
we have layer norms,
initially in the prenorm.
Now, we add them after the
nonlinearities in each block.
And now, we're throwing them
in both the Qs and the Ks.
And really, I think this is
getting at the stabilization
tricks that people
apply to this world.
Now, the final set of
things that I'll talk about
as a stability intervention,
and frankly, this one
is not as popular and more
of a Google-specific trick
that I've seen, but
logit soft-capping
is a much harder intervention
that some people apply.
So this one, in QK
norm, what we're doing
is we are controlling
the inputs to the softmax
and hoping that the
outputs are well-behaved.
If we really, really want to
enforce well-behaved outputs,
what we can do is we can take
the logits, the things that
go straight into the softmax,
and we can just cap them off,
so they can never be
too large or too small.
This is almost a
hard constraint.
It's called a soft
cap, of course,
but a Tanh is bounded
at some value.
And so this is in
the Gemma models.
I think Gemma 2, 3, and 4 all
use the logit soft cap trick.
And what they do
is they take all
of their logits for
the attention layers,
and then they soft cap
them at some value.
Some NVIDIA folks have done
actually quite nice work
doing systematic comparisons of
these stability interventions.
And what they find is, if you
start with a baseline model,
you can do all sorts of
different interventions.
And QK norm is here.
And it does slightly
better due to the fact
that you can crank up the
learning rate a little bit.
But if you do
soft-capping alone,
you actually end up
losing performance.
So there is a quality
degradation that happens.
This is a very
strong intervention.
You can never express
very confident signals
in your softmax beyond
a certain point.
So it does have some
negative consequences,
but this is a very
safe way of stabilizing
the outputs of your
attention-- or sorry,
the inputs to your
attention, the logits that
go into the softmax.
So that's the end of the
stability components.
I can pause for a moment here.
And I'll talk about various
attention things after that.
Cool.
OK.
All right.
So the last thing I
want to talk about today
is various interventions that
you can make to your attention.
And as I was saying at the
beginning of this lecture,
I'm only going to talk
about all the things
that you can do to dance
all by all attention today.
So if you were interested
in hearing about state space
models or linear time
attention, sadly, today
is not the day for you.
The things that I do
want to talk about,
which are really commonly
implemented attention
interventions today, are
group query attention,
which really saves inference
costs by reducing the number
of heads and sparse or
sliding window attention,
which really originally came
from the GPT 3-ish family,
but have now really been adopted
widely by most models that are
looking to do long context,
unless they're doing exotic SSM
stuff.
So I'll start with group query
attention, or GQA, or MQA.
I'm going to first set up the
need for these kinds of things.
And then you'll hopefully
see what the trick is
and why it's fairly natural.
So for the moment,
we've been talking
about training, and modeling,
and all these things,
but let's take a pause.
And now, let's think
about deployment.
You've trained this
very big model.
And now, you need to
serve it to lots of users.
And you're going to
pay a cost for serving.
And you're going to have
to, in abstract sense,
pay for two different resources.
You're going to have to pay
for your flops, the computation
that you're performing.
But you also have to
pay for another thing.
You have to pay for
your memory accesses.
Because the memory
accesses are also
going to impact your systems
characteristics, your latency,
your utilization.
So you want both of
these things to be small.
Now, let's think
about what happens
during training
or alternatively,
prefill, when you're
looking at your prompt,
where someone gives
you the stuff.
In this case, the total
arithmetic operations you have
is order of magnitude,
batch size, sequence length,
hidden dim squared.
That's roughly the size
of things that you get.
And of course, we're
doing quadratic attention,
so we've got d squared.
We've got total memory accesses.
What is our memory
access that we have here?
We have batch times sequence
length times hidden dim
plus the cost of
the softmax, which
has an n squared component.
And then we've got a d squared
component for the projections.
So the arithmetic intensity
here is pretty good.
It's going to be 1 over k.
This is the number of heads.
So you need to have,
sorry, head dims.
So your head dims
need to be big enough
that you're multiplying some
reasonably sized matrices.
And you've got a 1 over
bn, so your sequences
need to be long enough
or your batch sizes
need to be big enough.
As long as both
of these are true,
your GPUs are going
to be fully utilized.
Great.
You're using all
of your resources.
Now, we have finished training.
And now, we're
serving our users.
How do we serve our users?
We're going to generate
tokens and send it to them.
Now, if we're doing that, I
can't parallelize the generation
process.
What I'm going to do is, I'm
going to generate a token.
I'm going to condition on it.
I'm going to generate
the next token.
And I'm going to repeat
this process one by one.
This is just the curse of
autoregressive language
modeling.
We have to do this.
In order to do this, the
efficient way to do it
is to maintain all of
the passkeys and queries
that I've had in what's
called a KV cache.
So the KV cache is going to
maintain this matrix of Q dot
K over the past.
And then whenever I need
to compute something new,
I can reuse the submatrices that
I've already had from the past.
And I only really
need to compute
the new query key interactions
that I need to fill out
the rest of this matrix.
So every submatrix I've
computed before, I can keep.
I only need to
compute my new one.
So this saves a lot on compute.
That's great.
But the issue here is, now,
our arithmetic intensity
is not so good.
As you might intuit,
this KV cache approach
is going to be reading
parameters all the time.
Each time I have a
new step, I'm going
to have to read
in my parameters.
I'm going to have to
take these dot products.
And I'm going to do
this once every step.
And so now, what do I have?
Well, you my total
memory-- oh, sorry.
My total arithmetic
operations are the same.
I'm multiplying the same
matrices still, just
incrementally rather
than all at once.
But because I'm doing
this incrementally,
now, I have a memory
access pattern of batch
by sequence, squared by
hidden dim plus sequence
by hidden dim squared.
And the second term
is not so pleasant.
It used to be that it
was just d squared,
but now, we've got
n times d squared.
And if we compute the
arithmetic intensity, which
is the ratio of these two guys,
now, we have n over d plus 1
over b.
So now, what we need is large
batches plus short sequence
length or we need really
big model dimensions.
So if we want to serve a
small model efficiently,
this is not so good.
This is really
difficult to deal with.
This n over d term, this
first term over here,
which is sequence
length over hidden dim,
is very difficult to
reduce if we're doing
this incremental computation.
This is just a hard
thing to deal with.
So this leads to this idea of
MQA, or Multi-Query Attention.
Normally, you have
multiple heads
in your attention operation.
And you're going to
have different keys,
different values, and
different queries.
That's normally
how you do things.
But one thing that
we could do is, maybe
we can keep the Ks and the Vs
the same across all the heads.
And the only thing that's
different across the heads
are the queries.
If we do this, then
this drastically
removes the amount of
items that need to be
moved in and out of memory.
Because the KV cache are
now significantly smaller.
These are all shared
across all the heads.
This significantly reduces the
total memory access as well as
the arithmetic intensity.
And the key term that we
were talking about here,
we had the n over d term.
Now, we have h multiplying this.
And so this h term allows us
to significantly reduce the--
sorry, increase the
arithmetic intensity
if we have a lot of heads.
This is a significant gain
over what we had before.
So this gets us significant
efficiency improvements,
but the issue with MQA,
this is on the right here,
you have one value and one
key for all these queries,
you do, in fact, lose
significant expressive power
if you do this.
And so there's this trade off
between systems efficiency
and expressiveness.
And you might wonder,
is there a sweet spot
in which we can
avoid trading off
quite significantly expressive
power and computation?
And that's where GQA, or Grouped
Query Attention, comes in.
The original transformer
is multihead.
We have queries and
keys for each head.
In multi-query, we have
one key and value for each.
For all the heads
in grouped query,
we reduce the amount
of keys and values,
but we keep the number
of queries the same.
So we now have this ratio
that we can play with,
which is the number key
heads or the number of value
heads while keeping the total
number of heads much larger
than that.
So this allows us to
very simply control
the trade offs between
expressiveness and inference
efficiency.
There are other tricks from
DeepSeek V2, multihead latent
attention that I'll
mention briefly next time,
which have a different kind
of factorization structure
and a different
set of trade offs.
But really, the
nice thing about GQA
is that, in practice, the
trade off is quite favorable.
So if you have multihead,
your performance,
this was in, I think, T5
days, if I remember right.
This is your downstream
model performance.
This is your time per sample.
You want to reduce this
as much as possible.
With multihead
attention, you have best
performance but very high cost.
With MQA, you have lower cost
but much lower performance.
Similarly, if you make
your model smaller
to try to hit your
performance targets,
you get much worse
performance, GQA really
does get the best
of both worlds.
Very low inference cost,
nearly the same performance
as your full multihead.
And you see this
GQA group structure,
where if you have a small
reduction in the number
of heads, you
basically have most
of the gains in your
performance, which
allows you to keep most
of the expressive power
while getting significant
inference improvements.
And Percy will talk a bunch more
about the inference mechanics
later, but this should give
you a flavor why models today,
almost all, adopt this GQA
structure, because it gives you
a lot of this
inference cost, which
is really critical, without very
much of a expressiveness hit.
Cool.
Any questions for
GQA or KV cache?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE] given that you
have so many rules of thumbs
for what hyperparameters are
[INAUDIBLE] to what extent are
you still searching
over hyperparameters
versus exploiting these
rules of thumb [INAUDIBLE]?
I think it's a mix of both.
I think every model
training run has some thesis
about what can be varied.
And so you see this in a
lot of the reports, where
I think the hyperparameters
are often not where people are
touching too much, but you
see architecture changes one
at a time in a lot
of these reports.
But it's very rare to go
and change everything up.
I think Google is one
of the only orgs that
seems to really spice things
up in a significant way.
The Gemma series has done some
pretty interesting things.
The most recent Gemma
4 release, for example,
now has an individual embedding
for every layer in a way
to control the trade offs
between memory use and flops.
It's a very interesting set
of things that they've done.
Oh, yeah.
Back there.
[INAUDIBLE] experiments
with dynamically
altering some of these
parameters during training.
During training.
Let me think.
Weight decay, yes.
Weight decay, people change
in concert with learning rate.
That is actually a
heuristic that people do.
That works very well.
Other than that, I
don't know if there's
a lot of different hypers that
people change during training,
especially because the
architecture ones just
make training incompatible.
So you can't really change
them while you're training.
So I think weight
decay is probably
the one that I can think of.
The others are usually fixed.
Yeah.
So [INAUDIBLE] MQA, it's
not just inference time,
it's a [INAUDIBLE].
That's right.
Yeah.
You train with a certain
number of repeats.
Cool.
The last thing I'll talk about
is sliding window attention,
which is a really old idea.
GPT 3 used, actually, this--
if you read the paper,
they'll say, we alternate
between full attention, where
every position can attend
to everyone in the past,
and a banded matrix
style attention,
where you can attend to
everyone within a fixed window.
And OpenAI has some early
work on these different kinds
of attention patterns
that you can use.
But actually, this has
become really, really popular
over the past year.
This idea of alternating the
big, full attention and a more
local attention actually
hits a sweet spot
for how to manage long
context performance while not
paying too much for inference.
I think the more recent
revival in open models,
I would maybe say,
Cohere Command
A was the first one I saw do it,
where they had this structure,
where every four layers, they
would have a full attention that
attended to everything.
The three layers in between
would use a sliding window
attention that would only be
able to look at local structure.
And of course, as you go
up, sorry, in this case,
down, because they ordered
the diagram the other way,
as you go down
these blocks, you're
aggregating local
information into global ones.
So the local
attentions at the end
can, of course, access
more global information,
but this allows you to manage
the cost of having a really
long context
without having to go
for something like
a state space model
or a more exotic intervention.
And that's worked quite well.
There's also some
innovation, where
people change the embedding
format for the long range
information, where they get
rid of things like RoPE.
So you have no position
embeddings at all.
So you're really
looking, almost,
at bags, where the short
range information still
gets position information.
So people do all sorts kinds
of interventions involving
these both embeddings
and alternating
local and global structure.
I'll say that this is
attention and in general,
how to manage the trade
off between long context
cost and performance is still
an active area of investigation.
It's a place, where the most
architecture work and changes
are still being done.
We see, essentially, a bunch of
other models adopt this idea--
Llama 4, most recently,
Gemma 4, OLMo 3,
they all do this
combination of sliding
window attention and full
attention, in their case,
using full RoPE instead
of NoPE as the embedding.
So as I said, this is becoming
really, really popular.
Qwen3.5, which I've
put on the right,
they're actually a
little bit different,
because they alternate a state
space model called gated delta
net and one full attention
for every four layers.
So it's the same
alternating structure,
but they're using a
different cheap layer.
In their case, they're
using a state space model,
I'll explain what that is
next lecture, instead of
a sliding window
local attention.
But you see, this is
like, I think, a new theme
over the past year, where
open models are really
trying to grapple with
long context performance.
And the way to do
that, at least,
so far, is to have these
hybrid models that aren't just
global attention, aren't
just cheap attention,
they're some of mix in between.
And that seems to have
worked very well so
far in a lot of these models.
OK.
Cool.
So as I was trying
to emphasize, when
you look across all
of these models,
you start to see
a lot of patterns,
and hopefully, a sense
of general understanding
about what things you can do and
what things are good defaults.
We also see a lot of differences
in how we handle context
and how we handle
position embeddings.
Even tokenization,
there's some differences.
So there are differences
across these models,
but there's also commonalities
that hopefully, now, give you
some intuition as you go
out, and do your assignments,
and mess with the
leaderboard and so on.
Thanks.